Guide to the Cornell University examinations, 1869-1931.
Cornell University examinations,
- Series I. Examination Questions - Assorted
  - Physics - C - Mechanics, Fall Term, 1875 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; questions 1-6 and problems 7-9; question 1 begins: "What are the French and English standards of mass?"
  - Physics - Elictricity, Undated (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; possible typo in original title; possibly "Electricity"; "Phil Barnard" written at the top; annotated; 5 questions; question 1 begins: "What is the relation between the magnitudes of …"
  - Physics - A - Electricity and Magnetism, Winter and Spring Terms, 1875 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; 5 questions; question 1(a): "Define potential"
  - Physics - B - Electricity and Magnetism, Winter and Spring Terms, 1875 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; light drawings; 5 questions; question 1(a) begins: "Describe the phenomena of statical induction"
  - Physics - C - Acoustics and Optics, Winter Term, 1876 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; lightly annotated; questions 1-4, questions 5-6 under "OPTICS"; question 1 begins: "What is necessary to cause reflection of sound?"
  - Physics - Electricity and Magnetism, 1876-06 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; "Ph. Barnard at the top"; 10 questions; question 1 begins: "Describe the friction electric machine (plate machine)"
  - Physics - C - Optics, Summer Term, 1876 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; questions 1-5; questions 6-8 under "Those who did not pass the examination in March may answer the following questions in addition to the above."; question 1 begins: "Describe the Magic lantern"
  - Physics - Mechanics, 1876-12 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; handwritten exam; 12 questions; question 1: "Define Velocity, Acceleration, Force, Unit of Force"
  - Physics - Heat, 1876-12 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; handwritten exam; 12 questions; question 1: "Distinguish between the real and apparent expansions of a liquid"
  - Physics - Acoustics and Optics, Winter Term, 1877-03-19 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; handwritten exam; 2 pages 12 questions; question 1 begins: "Explain the transmission of sound through an elastic medium"
  - Physics - Optics, 1877-06 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; 12 questions; question 1: "Define Real focus, Vitrual focus, conjugate foci"
  - Problem Set - Due by October 23, Undated (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; 7 questions; question 1 begins: "Where is the centre of gravity of this series of weights?"
  - Physics - Heat, 1877-12 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; lightly annotated; questions 1-10 and problems 1-3; question 1 begins: "What are the various effects of heat?"
  - Physics - Acoustics and Optics, Winter Term, 1878 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; question 1-6 under Acoustics; questions 7-12 under "OPTICS"; question 1 begins: "How is sound produced?"
  - Physics - Optics, Summer Term, 1878 (Box 1, Volume 2)
  - Physics - Electricity and Magnetism, 1878-09 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; handwritten exam; 10 questions; question 1 begins: "Describe the fundamental phenomena of electrical attraction and repulsion"
  - Physics - Mechanics, 1878-09 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; handwritten exam; 10 questions; question 1: "Describe the units of length, mass, and time"
  - Physics - Heat, 1878-09 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; handwritten exam; 8-9 questions; part of the page ripped off; question 1 begins: "Describe the thermometric scales in use"
  - Physics - Acoustics and Optics, Winter Term, 1878 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; questions 1-6 under Acoustics; questions 7-12 under "OPTICS"; question 1 begins: "How is sound produced? What is the distinction between noise and music?"
  - Physics - Mechanics, Fall, 1878 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; 12 questions; question 1: "Define veolocity; acceleration; force; work; energy"
  - Physics - Electricity and Magnetism- Special Examination for Engineers, 1879-05-24 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; 9 to 12 Saturday; 10 questions; question 1: "Find the expression for the resistance of three conductors in Multiple Arc"
  - Physics - Electricity and Magnetism, 1879-06-10 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; 10 questions; question 1 begins: "Three copper wires, lengths 3, 8, and 10 metres; …"
  - Examination in Architecture - Building Materials and Construction - Sophomore. Spring Term, 1874 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; 20 questions (I - XX); 2 pages front and back; question I: "Name the kinds of stone commonly used in building, and classify them geologically"
  - Cornell University - Junior Examination in Architecture, Fall Term, 1874 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; 20 questions (I - XX); question I: "Sketch, and give the names of the mouldings used in Greek Architecture"
  - Department of Architecture - Examination in Building Materials and Construction, Spring Term, 1875 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; 2 pages (2 copies of each); 20 questions (I - XX); question III begins: "Explain the proper method of making concrete …"
  - Senior Examination in Architecture, Spring Term, 1875 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; 14 questions (I - XIV); question I begins: "What style of Architecture affords the best examples of …"
  - Cornell University - Senior Examination in Architecture, Spring Term, 1876 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; 12 questions (I - XII); question I begins: "Name the two systems of heating"
  - Architecture - Cornell University - Exam Questions, S.S. and Perspective, Juniors, Fall Term, 1878-12-20 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; handwritten in purple ink; 7 questions; drawn figures; question 1: "Define brillant point, curve of shade and shadow"
  - Architecture - "Methods of accomplishing or covering the transition from the square corner of a tower to the side of the octagon of a belfry or spire", Undated (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; 29 methods; method 1: "Tower gabled on all sides"
  - Architecture - Pressure of Wind on Roofs, Undated (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; handwritten; page has the problem set-up with a table of values; "Let P be the horizontal force of the wind in lbs per square foot --"
  - Architecture - A part of an exam, Undated (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; handwritten; questions 16-18; question 16 begins: "What is the horizontal thrust of a beam of white pine"
  - Architecture Exam, Undated (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; 13 questions; question 13 was cut and pasted onto the page; 2 pages; question 1 begins: "To what amount of tensile strain may a white pine timber …"
  - Architecture - A part of an exam, "Rafters, struts, and tie-beam of white pine", Undated (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; question 21 (or 27, could not discern completely); figure drawing; question: "Determine the strains and proper cross-sections of pieces"
  - Architecture - "Methods of accomplishing or covering the transition from the square corner of a tower to the side of the octagon of a belfry or spire" - Another Copy, Undated (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; horizontal
  - Architecture - Examination in Building Materials and Construction, Spring Term, 1877 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; handwritten exam; 2 pages; 20 questions (I - XX); question I begins: "Name three kinds of stone commonly used in building"
  - Subjects and Questions for Examination in Psychology, Fall Term, 1875-1876 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; divided into 12 sections (labled as "No.1" to "No. 12") with 3 questions each; question 1 of No.1: "Describe the white nerve matter and its distribution throughout the body"
  - Subjects and Questions for Examination in Psychology, Fall Term, 1877-1878 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; divided into 12 sections (labled as "No.1" to "No. 12") with 3 questions each; annotated; question 1 of No.7: "Point out the difference between the sensation of …"
  - Examination in Structural and Economic Geology, 1878-03-25 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; "Phil Barnard" written on the front; annotated; questions 35-67; question 35: "Phenomena and composition of 'dust showers' and 'blood rains.' What is 'red snow'?"
  - Examination in General Geology, 1878-12-19 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; divided into 6 sets (I. Physiography, II. Lithology, III. Petrology,etc., IV. Dynamical Geology, V. Historical Geology, VI. Miscellaneous) each with a set of questions; 22 questions in total
  - Physiological Botany, Final Examination, 1877-06-11 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; 20 questions; question 1 begins: "Give a definition of each of the following parts of plants …"
  - Cornell University - Astronomy, Prof. Potter, Undated (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; lightly annotated; 12 questions (I - XII); question I: "Explain the difference between the Sidereal and Solar days"
  - Military Science, 1878-03-26 (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; handwritten exam on lined paper; 13 questions; question 1: "Define discipline as applied to organization od modern armies"
  - Sand Surveying, Undated (Box 1, Volume 2)
    Gift from The Chi of Psi Upsilon Chapter; handwritten in purple ink; 2 pages; 14 questions (I - XIV); question I begins: "Describe briefly the different kinds of …"
  - Assorted Exams and Non-Exams (1 of 3), 1870-1884, 1917, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Cornell University - Examination in History, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    14 questions; question 1 begins: "Give briefly and concisely the main causes of the Revival of Learning …"; 2 questions under Questions on Macaulay's Essays; Essay on Barrère; On Buckle's History of Civilization in England
  - The Cornell University - Examination in History, First Year Class, 1870-03-31 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    8 sections (I - VIII); various number of questions for each; question III.1: "To which of the above families do the East Indians belong?"
  - The Cornell University - Examination in History, Second Year Class, 1870-04-02 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    9 sections (I - IX); various number of questions for each; question I.1: "Who were the original Italians?"
  - The Cornell University - The College of History, Second Year Class, Third Trimester, 1870-06-25 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    19 questions; question 1 begins: "What were the powers of the Emperor Augustus and of his immediate successors?"
  - The Cornell University - Department of History, Second Year Class, 1871-06-13 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    7 sections (I - VII); various number of questions for each; question I.1: "What were the principal causes of the decline and fall of the Roman Empire."
  - Cornell University - Department of History, Third Year Class, Fall Trimester, 1871 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    13 sections (I - XIII); question II(a): "Which was the first dynasty of French kings?"
  - The Cornell University - College of History, Sophomore Class, 1871-03-15 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    13 questions; question 1 begins: "What was the first form of government at Rome?"
  - The Cornell University - College of History, Third Year, Fall Trimester, 1870-1871 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    12 questions; question 1 begins: "What is meant by the history of European civilization?"
  - Cornell University - Department of History, Third Year Class, Fall Trimester, 1872 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Year was rewritten on exam; 12 sections (I - XII); question I(a): "Who were the inhabitants of Gaul when the Franks invaded it?"
  - Cornell University - College of History - Department of Ancient History, First Year Class, 1872-03-19 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    10 sections (I - X); question I: "What advantages may arise from the study of History?"
  - Cornell University - College of History - Department of Roman History, Second Year Class, 1872-03-20 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    10 sections (I - X); question I.1: "What authority is there for the early history of Rome?"
  - Cornell University - Department of History, Second Year, 3rd Term, 1872-06-17 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Exam in purple ink; 15 sections (I - XV); question I begins: "What different offices and powers did Augustus and …"
  - The Cornell University - Department of History, Second Year Class, Winter Term, 1873-03-19 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    12 questions; question 1 begins: "In the early times of Rome, what was the distinction between …"
  - The Cornell University - The College of History, Second Year Class, 1873-06-20 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    21 questions; question 2 begins: "After the time of the Antonines, what body virtually appointed the Emperor?"
  - Cornell University - Department of History, Third Year Class, 1873-12-15 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Exam in red ink; 10 sections (I - X); question I.1: "Describe the Celtic character and religion"
  - Cornell University - College of History, Second Year Class, Winter Term, 1874-03-18 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    14 questions (I - XIV); question I: "Describe the Constitution of Romulus, and the division into tribes, curiӕ, centuries, and gentes?"
  - Cornell University - College of History - Ancient History, First Year Class, 1874-06-22 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    9 sections (I - IX); question I.1: "What are the characteristics of the Mongolians?"
  - Cornell University - History of the Decline and Fall of Rome, Second Year Class, 1874-06-24 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    11 sections (I - XI); question I.1: "Describe the character of Julius Cӕsar."
  - Cornell University - History of the Decline and Fall of Rome, Second Year Class (Another Copy), 1874-06-24 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Lightly annotated
  - Cornell University - Modern History - Close of Second Term, Class of 1874, A.D. White, 1874 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    12 questions; question 1 begins: "The good and evil effects of the Scholastic Philosophy …"; "OPTIONAL EXAMINATION" section with parts A, B, C
  - The Cornell University - Department of History, Third Year, Third Term, 1875-06-10 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    19 questions; question 1 begins: "What was the Constitution of the Roman Empire under Augustus?"
  - Modern History - First Term, 1881-12-14 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    14 questions; question 1 begins: "What was the effect of the great maritime discoveries upon the paths of commerce, --"
  - Modern History - Second Term, 1882-03-22 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    12 questions; question 1: "State the political results of the Thirty Years' War."
  - Modern History - Third Term, 1882-06-07 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    7 questions; question 1: "What was the Congress of Vienna, and what were its chief political results?"
  - Junior American History - Winter Term, 1884-03-21 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Handwritten title, date written on the back, 18 questions; question 1: "Causes of King Philip's war."
  - Examination in Literature - Fourth Year, Fall Term, 1872-1873 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    20 questions; question 1: "What are the fine arts?"
  - The Cornell University - Examination in Shakespeare's Macbeth, Senior Class, 1873-03-17 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    15 questions; question 1 begins: "How does the opening of Macbeth contrast with that of Hamlet …"
  - Examination in Shakespeare's "Othello" - Fourth Year, Spring Term, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    20 questions; question 1: "How does Shakespeare idealize his characters?"
  - Literature - Fourth Year, Fall Term, 1873-1874 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    71 questions; question 1: "The Law of Evolution in Literature"; question 50 misnumbered as question 55
  - Cornell University - Literature - Professor Shackford, Fourth Year, Winter Term, 1874 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    23 questions; question 1 begins: "State the principal Historical Art-Epics …"
  - Comparative Literature - Professor Shackford, Senior Year, Third Term, 1875 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    30 questions; question 1: "In what respect is all criticism comparative"
  - Cornell University - Rhetoric - Professor Shackford, First Year, Winter Term, Second Section, 1874 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    12 questions; question 1: "Give an example of each degree of Personification"
  - Cornell University - Rhetoric - Professor Shackford, First Year, Third Term, 1875-06-08 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    3 sections (I-III); 8 questions for each section; question I.1: "What is the advantage of the participial construction?"
  - Examination in Rhetoric - Professor Shackford, Freshman Year, Second Term, 1876 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    9 questions; question 9 has parts (a)-(l) and parts (d) and ( e) are repeated twice; question 1 begins: "The expansion and the enlargement …"
  - Rhetoric - Professor Shackford, Freshman Year, Third Term, Undated (Box 2, Volume 1)
    20 questions; question 1 begins: "Explain by examples the figurative nature of language …"
  - Cornell University - Professor Shackford, Undated (Box 2, Volume 1)
    3 sections (I-III); 24 questions total but two questions are numbered 7; question I.1: "From what does Antithesis derive its force?"
  - Cornell University - History and Elements of the English Language - Freshman Year, First Term, Undated (Box 2, Volume 1)
    15 questions; question 1: "What classes of words in English are of Saxon origin?"
  - Cornell University - History and Elements of the English Language - Prof. Shackford, First Year, Third Term (1 of 2), 1874 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    30 questions; question 1: "When is it inferred that different languages are derived from the same source?
  - Cornell University - History and Elements of the English Language - Prof. Shackford, First Year, Third Term, Second Section (2 of 2), 1874 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    30 questions; question 1: "What are the great divisions or families of languages?"
  - Examination in Ancient Oratory - Fourth Year, Spring Term, 1873 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    25 questions; question 1: "The words orator and oration in their ancient and their modern sense."
  - Cornell University - Senior Examination in Grecian and Roman Oratory, 1874-06-10 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    40 questions; question 1: "What circumstances were favorable to the cultivation of Oratory in Greece?"
  - Cornell University - Ancient Oratory, 1874-12-16 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    20 questions; question 1: "What was the function of the Orator at Athens?"
  - Examination Papers on the Lectures on Geology - Delivered by Prof. Ch. Fred. Hartt, M.A., Spring Term, 1871-1872 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    Booklet format; 20 sections (I - XX); 5 questions in each section but two questions numbered 4 in section VI; question I.1 begins: "Describe Titanotherium, Palotherium, Megatherium"
  - Examination Papers on the Lectures on Geology - Delivered by Prof. Ch. Fred. Hartt, M.A., Winter Term, 1871-1872 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    Booklet format; 20 sections (I - XX); 5 questions in each section; question I.1 begins: "What are dykes, veins, faults, joints, planes of stratification, ripple marks, wave marks?"
  - Examination Papers on the Lectures on Geology - Delivered by Prof. Ch. Fred. Hartt, M.A., Spring Term, 1872-1873 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    Booklet format; annotated; 20 sections (I - XX); 5 questions in each section but two questions numbered 4 in section XV; question I.1: "What are atolls and how are they formed?"
  - Examination in Structural and Economic Geology - Winter Term, 1876-03-21 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    34 questions; question 1: "Scope and main divisions of Geology, with definitions"
  - Examination in Geology - Spring Term, 1876 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    16 questions; question 1: "Name ten of the most abundant rock-forming minerals, giving characters of three"
  - Examination Questions on the Lectures on the History and Criticism of Philosophy - Delivered before the Senior and Junior Classes - Prof. W.D. Wilson, Fall Term, 1871-1872 (Box 2, Volume 1)
    20 sections (I - XX); questions not numbered in order; not on the first page: "If these Examination questions are read in the order in which they are numbered, they will present a syllabus of the Lectures in the order in which they were delivered"; question I.1: "What is the proper scope of Metaphysics?"
  - Questions for the Use of The Class in Zoology - Winter Trimester, 1876-03-07 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    63 questions; initialed J.H.C. at the front page; question 1: "Name and give an account of the simplest organism described in this course"
  - The Cornell University - Junior Examination in Architecture, Fall Term, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    20 questions (I - XX); question I: "Define the terms 'Aesthetic' and 'Technical'"
  - The Cornell University - Examination in Physics - Electricity (Donated by Prof. E. G. Shalkhauser), 1871-06-12 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Handwritten and typed notes; actual exam has 10 questions and is annotated; question 1 begins: "What are the different departments or branches of the science of electricity …"
  - Assorted Exams and Non-Exams (2 of 3), 1870-1871 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Examination Questions on the Lectures on Political Economy - Delivered by Prof. W. D. Wilson, Before the Senior and Junior Classes, Winter Term, 1870-1871 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Booklet format; annotated; "William E. Holcomb" signed at the top but could not decipher completely; 20 sections (No. 1 - No. 20); questions not numbered in order; question No.1.1: "Define the nature and scope of Political Economy"
  - Assorted Exams and Non-Exams (3 of 3), 1871-1873, undated, ca. 1965 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Cornell University - Physiological Botany, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Piece of last page ripped off; dated June 17 (but no year); 2:30 p.m.; 16 questions; question 1: "How are Plants distinguished from Animals"
  - Cornell University - College of Languages - French Department - First Year Class, 1872-03-18 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    16 sentences to translate into French; sentence 1: "Bread and water are good for men. Wine is only good for the sick."
  - The Cornell University - French Department, First Year Class, Third Trimester, 1871-06-14 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    15 sentences to translate into French; one passage to translate to English; sentence 1 begins: "Has not your eldest sister changed her dress?"
  - The Cornell University - Examination in German - Winter Trimester, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    3 sections (I - III); question III.1 begins: "What is declension?"; "GRAHAM" written on the back
  - Cornell University - Rhetoric - Freshman Class, Spring Trimester, 1872-06-18 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Exam in purple ink; 20 questions; question 1: "What are the characteristics of Poetic Diction?"
  - Cornell University - German Department - Exam Papers (1 of 3), 1869-1879, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Cornell University - German Department - Exam Papers (2 of 3), 1880-1889 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Cornell University - German Department - Exam Papers (3 of 3), 1890-1895, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Cornell University - Examination Papers - Miscellaneous, 1889-1893, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    All papers initialed "K.J. 1893" at the bottom
  - Cornell University - Freshman Latin - Nepos, 1889-12-20 (Box 2, Folder 7)